Guide to the Ivan L. Bennett Speeches MC.53
New York University Archives
Ivan L. Bennett Speeches
1979-1981
New York University Archives
Bennett, Ivan L. (Ivan Loveridge), 1892-1980
MC.53
1 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes
Ivan L. Bennett was Acting President of New York University (NYU) from 1979 to 1981. This collection contains 76 speeches and remarks he delivered during his tenure, along with related correspondence, memoranda, and drafts.
Biographical Note
Ivan Loveridge Bennett, Jr., M.D., served as acting president of New York University (NYU) from 1979 to 1981, when John C. Sawhill left the position to serve as deputy secretary of the U.S. Department of Energy. Dr. Bennett was succeeded by John Brademas.
Dr. Bennett held numerous administrative positions at NYU before serving as acting president. On January 21, 1969, Bennett was appointed Vice-President for Health Affairs and Director of the NYU Medical Center. On May 8, 1970, he was appointed director of the School of Medicine and Director of the Post-Graduate Medical School. (Bennett was the first person to hold both positions simultaneously.) In 1970 he became Dean of the New York University School of Medicine; in 1973 he was appointed Provost of the New York University Medical Center; and in 1976 Bennett was named Executive Vice-President for Health Affairs. Bennett did not seek election as President of New York University in 1981, opting instead to return to the Medical Center.
Bennett's career as a medical researcher, professor, and administrator had been well established by the time he arrived at New York University. He was an Associate Professor of Internal Medicine at Yale University from 1952 to 1954. He then moved to Johns Hopkins University, where he served as an Associate Professor of Medicine until 1957, when he was made a full Professor. In 1958 Bennett was named the Baxley Professor of Pathology and the director of that department. Bennett took a leave of absence from Johns Hopkins University in 1966 to become the Deputy Director and, later, Acting Director of U.S. President Lyndon B. Johnson's Office of Science and Technology.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains 76 speeches and series of remarks delivered by Ivan L. Bennett between 1979 and 1981, during his tenure as acting president of New York University. This collection also includes related materials, including correspondence, memoranda, and drafts. The speeches are arranged chronologically: Box 1 contains addresses and remarks delivered between March 1979 and June 1980 and Box 2 contains speeches and remarks presented from July 1980 and June 1981.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was transferred from the President's Office to the Archives by Judith Chazen Walsh at the request of Lynne Brown, Assistant to the President, on June 8, 1981.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open without restrictions.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged chronologically.
New York University; New York University. Office of the President
- "Principles for Improving Health in the Developing World," Rockefeller Foundation, March 1979 and May 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Hebrew Union College Dedication Dinner, Plaza Hotel, October 29, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Dental Associates Dinner, St. Regis, October 31, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "The Future of Academic Medicine," Annual Meeting of the Association of Program Directors in Internal Medicine, Washington Hilton Hotel, Washington, D. C., November 3, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Special Convocation, NYU Medical Center, November 10, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Chet Huntley Memorial Lecture, November 15, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Dental Associates Fall Alumni Meeting and Deans Day, Sheraton Center, November 16, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "Medicine, Technology and Society," Bristol Premedical Society, NYU, November 20, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Luncheon for Chinese Delegation, NYU, November 26, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Alumni Federation Reception, NYU, November 29, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Commerce Alumni Association, 29th Annual Dean's Day, December 1, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Meeting of the New York Alliance for Public Education, December 12, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Urban Studies Center Press Conference, NYU, December 17, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- "The Planning of Research: The Role of the Federal Government," coauthored with Thomas J. Kennedy, Jr., in The Social Context of Medical Research (Harvard University Press, 1980), 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Scope and contents
  Only correspondence relating to this lecture exists in this folder.
- Quote for Proposed Article in Medical Center News, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Quote re: "Demands of Increased Competition," The Herald Statesman (Yonkers, N.Y.), January 3, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Meeting of Council of Friends of the Institute of Fine Arts, February 27, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Announcement of New Dean for the Graduate School of Business Administration, March 18, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Graduate School of Arts and Science Alumni Day, March 22, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Richard Ettinghausen Library Dedication, April 3, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- "Medicine, Technology and Society," Princeton University Pre-Medical Society, April 9, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Eastern Comparative Literature Conference, NYU, May 3, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- School of Social Work 20th Anniversary Reception Honoring Dr. Ruth Lewis Farkas, NYU, April 20, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- "America's Confrontation with the American Dream," Founders Day Address, April 24, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- "Medicine, Technology and Society," Alpha Omega Alpha Lecture, Ohio State University, May 7, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Afro-American Institute Conference, NYU, May 23, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Alumni Federation Annual Dinner, NYU, May 28, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- NYU Medical School Graduating Class Dinner Dance, June 3, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Graduate School of Business Administration Pre-Commencement Ceremony, June 4, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Introduction of Honorary Degree Recipients, Annual Trustees Dinner, NYU, June 4, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Commencement Address, New York University, June 5, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Second World Congress on Antisepsis, NYU Medical Center, June 12, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  Scope and Contents
  Copy of remarks not in folder. Folder contains letters regarding the event.
- Basic Text for General Ivan L. Bennett's Obituary, June 18, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Graduate School of Business Administration Partners Dinner Honoring William R. Dill, June 26, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Graduation Ceremony Remarks, NYU College of Dentistry, June 26, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Careers in Business Reception, NYU, July 10, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- School of Social Work Faculty Meeting, September 3, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Report to the Library Faculty, September 18, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Report to the Dental Faculty, September 18, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- "Medicine, Technology and Society," The Twenty-Second Tinsley R. Harrison Memorial Lecture, University of Alabama in Birmingham, Sepember 22, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  General
  Also published in the Alabama Journal of Medical Sciences, Vol 18, No. 1, 1980
- Report to the Graduate School of Public Administration Faculty, September 23, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- The Albert Gallatin Associates Dinner in Honor of John M. Schiff, October 2, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Report to the Faculty of Arts and Science, October 6, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Report to the Faculty of Business Administration, October 8, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Dedication of Judge Abraham Lieberman Reading Room, NYU Law School, October 22, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Eulogy for Gladys Houx Rusk, October 24, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Dental Associates Dinner in Honor of Dr. S. Sigmund Stahl, St. Regis-Sheraton Hotel, November 5, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- The Charles Waldo Haskins Associates of the College of Business and Public Administration Dinner in Honor of Arjay Miller, November 12, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- The Arthur T. Vanderbilt Associates Dinner in Honor of Whitney North Seymour, Sr., November 12, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Chet Huntley Memorial Lecture, NYU, November 13, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- NYU Dentistry Alumni Day, November 14, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- NYU California Alumni Club, Los Angeles, California, November 15, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Graduate School of Business Administration Alumni Dinner, November 17, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Washington Square and University College Dedication of Lounge from Class of 1929, November 21, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- College of Business and Public Administration, School of Education, Health, Nursing, and Arts Professions Parents Day, November 23, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Publication of Volume II of the William Livingston Papers, NYU, December 3, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- NYU Alumnae Club, Inc., Woman of Achievement Awards Reception and Presentation in Honor of Dr. Ruth Lewis Farkas, December 4, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Academic Convocation for the Installation of William Frederic May as Dean of the Faculty of Business Administration and Dean of the Graduate School of Business Administration, Decemer 8, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Inaugural Lecture in the Humanities, Issac Bashevis Singer, Rockefeller University, December 8, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- 25-Year Service Awards Reception, NYU, January 21, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Gold Medal Dinner Honoring Walter Cronkite, Palm Beach, Florida, February 1, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- United Nations Reform Conference, NYU, February 19, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Real Estate Institute (NYU) Dinner, Waldorf Astoria, March 19, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Convocation Honoring Madam Sadat, March 25, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Luncheon Honoring Madam Sadat, March 25, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Dinner Preceding Founders Day Honors Convocation, April 23, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Founders Day Convocation Honoring Lord Noel Gilroy Annan, April 23, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Commerce Alumni Dinner, Waldorf Astoria, May 6, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Gallatin Associates Dinner, May 19, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Medical University of South Carolina, Charleston, S.C., May 21, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Alumni Federation Dinner, NYU Club, May 21, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Testimonial Dinner to Theodore E. Woodward, M.D., University of Maryland, Baltimore, Maryland, May 22, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- "Medicine, Technology and Society," The William Resnik Memorial Lecture, Stamford, Connecticut, May 27, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Graduate School of Business Administration Pre-Commencement Exercise, Trinity Church, June 3, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Introduction of Honorary Degree Recipients, Annual Trustees Dinner, NYU, June 3, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Commencement Address - New York University, June 4, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- New York University Association in France, n.d (Box 2, Folder 42)
- List of Speeches, 1979 -1981 (Box 2, Folder 43)